If you'd like to learn how to play the lobster, we have some here.
إذا أردت أن تتعلم كيف تلعب لعبة الكركند ,فلدينا بعض منهم هنا.
And that's not a joke, we really do.
و هي ليست مزحة , بالفعل لدينا.
So come up afterwards and I'll show you how to play a lobster.
فتعالوا بعد العرض و سأريكم كيف تلعبون الكركند.
So, actually, I started working on what's called the mantis shrimp
حسنا, في الواقع بدأت أعمل مع ما يدعى بقريدس فرس النبي
a few years ago because they make sound.
منذ بضعة سنوات لأنهم يصدرون أصوات.
This is a recording I made of a mantis shrimp
هذا تسجيل صنعته لقريدس فرس النبي
that's found off the coast of California.
الموجود على ساحل كاليفورنيا.
And while that's an absolutely fascinating sound,
و بالرغم من أن هذا الصوت رائع جدا,
it actually turns out to be a very difficult project.
إلا أنه إتضح أن هذا المشروع صعب للغاية.
And while I was struggling to figure out how and why mantis shrimp,
و بينما أنا اصارع لأعرف كيف و لماذا يصدر قريدس
or stomatopods, make sound, I started to think about their appendages.
فرس النبي أو الستومابود صوتا, بدأت أفكر في أطرافه.
And mantis shrimp are called "mantis shrimp" after the praying mantises,
و يدعى قريدس فرس النبي بهذا الأسم نسبة إلى سرعوف فرس النبي المصلي,
which also have a fast feeding appendage. And I started to think,
و الذي لديه أطراف سريعة للتغذية. و بدأت أفكر ,
well, maybe it will be interesting, while listening to their sounds,
حسنا ربما يكون من المثير,بينما أستمع إلى أصواتهم,
to figure out how these animals generate very fast feeding strikes.
أن أكتشف كيف تقوم تلك الحيوانات بتلك الضربات السريعة جدا.
And so today I'll talk about the extreme stomatopod strike,
إذن فاليوم سأحدثكم عن ضربة الستومابود الخارقة,
work that I've done in collaboration with Wyatt Korff and Roy Caldwell.
وهو ما أعمل عليه بالتعاون مع وايات كورف و روي كالدويل.
So, mantis shrimp come in two varieties:
إذن, قريدس فرس النبي له نوعان:
there are spearers and smashers.
هناك الطواعن و الكواسر.
And this is a spearing mantis shrimp, or stomatopod.
و هذا هو القريدس الطاعن أو الستومابود الطاعن.
And he lives in the sand, and he catches things that go by overhead.
و هو يعيش في الرمال و يمسك الأشياء التي تعبر فوقه.
So, a quick strike like that. And if we slow it down a bit,
بهذه الضربة السريعة هكذا. و لو أبطأناها قليلا,
this is the mantis shrimp -- the same species --
هذل قريدس فرس النبي --نفس الفصيلة--
recorded at 1,000 frames a second,
مسجَّل بمعدا 1000 لقطة في الثانية,
played back at 15 frames per second.
و يتم تشغيله ب15 لقطة في الثانية.
And you can see it's just a really spectacular extension of the limbs,
وكما ترون الإمتداد الرائع للأطراف
exploding upward to actually just catch
التي تنتفض لأعلى لتمسك فقط
a dead piece of shrimp that I had offered it.
قطعة من القريدس الميت التي وضعتها له.
Now, the other type of mantis shrimp is the smasher stomatopod,
الآن النوع الآخر من قريدس فرس النبي وهو الستومابود الكاسر,
and these guys open up snails for a living.
و هؤلاء يفتحون الحلزون ليتغذوا.
And so this guy gets the snail all set up and gives it a good whack.
إذن فهذا الأخ هنا يجهز الحلزون ثم يعطيه ضربة محترمة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, I'll play it one more time.
سأشغله مرة أخرى.
He wiggles it in place, tugs it with his nose, and smash.
يحركه في مكانه, يشِّده بأنفه ثم يضرب.
And a few smashes later, the snail is broken open, and he's got a good dinner.
و بعد بضعة ضربات ينفتح الحلزون و يأخذ عشائه اللذيذ.
So, the smasher raptorial appendage can stab with a point at the end,
إذن فهذه الأطراف الكاسرة الجارحة يمكن أن تطعن بالجزء المدبب في نهايتها,
or it can smash with the heel.
أو أن تحطم بالكعب.
And today I'll talk about the smashing type of strike.
و اليوم سأتحدث عن النوع الكاسر من الضربات.
And so the first question that came to mind was,
إذن فالسؤال الأول الذي يتبادر إلى الأذهان,
well, how fast does this limb move?
حسنا هو ما مدى سرعة حركة هذا الطرف؟
Because it's moving pretty darn fast on that video.
لأنه يتحرك بسرعة رهيبة في هذا الفيديو.
And I immediately came upon a problem.
و على الفور واجهتني مشكلة.
Every single high-speed video system in the biology department
كل واحد من أنظمة التصوير العالية السرعة في قسم الأحياء
at Berkeley wasn't fast enough to catch this movement.
في بيركلي لم يكن بالسرعة الكافية ليلتقط هذه الحركة.
We simply couldn't capture it on video.
ببساطة لم نستطع إلتقاطها بالفيديو.
And so this had me stymied for quite a long period of time.
و لقد وضعني هذا في وضع حرج لمدة طويلة
And then a BBC crew came cruising through the biology department,
ثم جاء فريق قناة BBC إلى قسم الأحياء,
looking for a story to do about new technologies in biology.
باحثين عن سبق جديد عن تكنولوجيا حديثة في علم الأحياء.
And so we struck up a deal.
فعقدنا إتفاقية
I said, "Well, if you guys rent the high-speed video system
قلت." حسنا إذا قمتم أنتم بتأجير نظام التصوير العالي السرعة
that could capture these movements,
الذي يستطيع إلتقاط هذه الحركة,
you guys can film us collecting the data."
يمكنكم تصويرنا و نحن نجمع البيانات."
And believe it or not, they went for it. (Laughter)
و صدق أولا تصدق, إقتنعوا بها.
So we got this incredible video system. It's very new technology --
و بالتالي حصلنا على نظام التصوير الرائع هذا. وهو تكنولوجيا حديثة للغاية--
it just came out about a year ago --
ظهرت فقط منذ عام واحد تقريبا--
that allows you to film at extremely high speeds in low light.
يسمح بتصوير سرعات عالية جدا في إضائة منخفضة.
And low light is a critical issue with filming animals,
و الإضاءة المنخفضه هي أساسية لتصوير الحيوانات,
because if it's too high, you fry them. (Laughter)
لأنها لو كانت عالية , فستحرقهم.
So this is a mantis shrimp. There are the eyes up here,
إذا فهذا هو قريدس فرس النبي. ها هي أعينه هنا
and there's that raptorial appendage, and there's the heel.
و ها هي الأطراف الكاسرة, و ها هو الكعب.
And that thing's going to swing around and smash the snail.
و هذا الشئ سيتأرجح و يكسر الحلزون.
And the snail's wired to a stick,
و هذا الحلزون مربوط بعصا,
so he's a little bit easier to set up the shot. And -- yeah.
ليسهل عملية تصوير اللقطة.و --نعم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I hope there aren't any snail rights activists around here.
أتمنى ألا يكون هناك مدافعين عن حقوق الحلزون هنا.
So this was filmed at 5,000 frames per second,
صُوِر هذا في نطاق 5.000 لقطة في الثانية,
and I'm playing it back at 15. And so this is slowed down 333 times.
و انا أعيد تشغيلها بمعدل 15. إذن فهي أبطا 333 مرة.
And as you'll notice, it's still pretty gosh darn fast
و ستلاحظون, إنها مازالت سريعة بشكل كبير
slowed down 333 times. It's an incredibly powerful movement.
حتى وهي مبطئة 333 مرة. إنها حركة قوية للغاية.
The whole limb extends out. The body flexes backwards --
كل الطرف يمتد إلى الخارج. كل الجسم ينثني إلى الوراء--
just a spectacular movement.
حركة مبهرة حقا.
And so what we did is, we took a look at these videos,
إذن فما فعلناه هو أننا ألقينا نظرة على هذه الفيديوهات,
and we measured how fast the limb was moving
و قمنا بقياس سرعة تحرك الطرف
to get back to that original question.
لنعود بذلك إلى السؤال الأساسي.
And we were in for our first surprise.
و قد كانت مفاجئتنا الأولى.
So what we calculated was that the limbs were moving
فما وجدناه كان أن الأطراف كانت تتحرك
at the peak speed ranging from 10 meters per second
بأقصى سرعة تتراوح مابين 10 متر في الثانية
all the way up to 23 meters per second.
حتى تصل إلى 23 متر في الثانية.
And for those of you who prefer miles per hour,
و إلى من يفضلون مقياس الأميال إلى الساعة,
that's over 45 miles per hour in water. And this is really darn fast.
هذا ما يتعدى ال 45 ميل في الساعة في الماء. وهذا سريع جدا.
In fact, it's so fast we were able to add a new point
في الواقع إنه سريع لدرجة اننا وضعنا حد جديد
on the extreme animal movement spectrum.
في مقياس الحركات الخارقة للحيوانات.
And mantis shrimp are officially the fastest measured feeding strike
و قريدس فرس النبي لديه رسميا أسرع ضربة تغذية مسجلة
of any animal system. So our first surprise.
في أي نظام حيواني. أول مفاجئاتنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So that was really cool and very unexpected.
إذا فهذا كان رائعا حقا و غير متوقع بالمرة.
So, you might be wondering, well, how do they do it?
و ربما تتسائلون ,حسنا, كيف يفعلون ذلك؟
And actually, this work was done in the 1960s
و في الواقع هذا العمل قام به في الستينات
by a famous biologist named Malcolm Burrows.
عالم أحياء مشهور يدعى مالكولم بوروز.
And what he showed in mantis shrimp is that they use
و ما وضحه في قريدس فرس النبي هو أنهم يستخدمون
what's called a "catch mechanism," or "click mechanism."
ما يدعى بميكانيكية القفل, أو ميكانيكية مزلاج الأمان.
And what this basically consists of is a large muscle
وهي في الأساس عبارة عن عضلة كبيرة
that takes a good long time to contract,
والتي تأخذ وقت طويل لتنقبض,
and a latch that prevents anything from moving.
و مزلاج يمنع أي جزء من الحركة .
So the muscle contracts, and nothing happens.
فتقبض العضلة دون أن يحدث أي شئ.
And once the muscle's contracted completely, everything's stored up --
و بمجرد إكتمال إنقباض العضلة تماما, وكل شئ متحفز--
the latch flies upward, and you've got the movement.
يطير المزلاج منفتحا و تحدث الحركة.
And that's basically what's called a "power amplification system."
و هذا هو ما يطلق عليه أساسا نظام مضاعفة القوى.
It takes a long time for the muscle to contract,
تأخذ العضلة وقتا طويلة لتنقبض,
and a very short time for the limb to fly out.
و وقت قصير جدا لأنبساط الطرف.
And so I thought that this was sort of the end of the story.
ففكرت أن هذه إذن هي نهاية القصة.
This was how mantis shrimps make these very fast strikes.
هذا هو كيف يقوم قريدس فرس النبي بهذه الضربات السريعة جدا.
But then I took a trip to the National Museum of Natural History.
و لكن بعد ذلك قمت برحلة إلى المتحف القومي للتاريخ الطبيعي.
And if any of you ever have a chance,
و لو كان لدى أحدكم الفرصة
backstage of the National Museum of Natural History
في خلفية المتحف القومي للتاريخ الطبيعي
is one of the world's best collections of preserved mantis shrimp. And what --
هناك مجموعة من أفضل مجموعات قريدس فرس النبي المحفوظة. و --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
this is serious business for me.
هذا أمر مهم بالنسبة لي.
So, this -- what I saw, on every single mantis shrimp limb,
إذن فما رأيته على ساق كل قريدس رأيته
whether it's a spearer or a smasher,
سواء كان طاعنا أو كاسرا,
is a beautiful saddle-shaped structure
هو تكوين جميل يشبه السرج
right on the top surface of the limb. And you can see it right here.
بالظبط على السطح العلوي للطرف. و يمكن رؤيته ها هنا.
It just looks like a saddle you'd put on a horse.
إنها تشبة بالظبط السرج الذي نضعه على الحصان.
It's a very beautiful structure.
إنه تكوين جميل حقا.
And it's surrounded by membranous areas. And those membranous areas
وهو محاط بمنطقة غشائية. و تلك المناطق الغشائية
suggested to me that maybe this is some kind of dynamically flexible structure.
أوحت لى أنه ربما هذا التكوين هو نوع من التركيبات المرنة المتحركة.
And this really sort of had me scratching my head for a while.
و لقد جعلني هذا أحك رأسي مفكرةً لمدة من الوقت.
And then we did a series of calculations, and what we were able to show
ثم قمنا بمجموعة من الحسابات, و ما تمكنا من إيضاحه
is that these mantis shrimp have to have a spring.
هو أنه يجب أن يحتوى جسم القريدس على زنبرك.
There needs to be some kind of spring-loaded mechanism
بالتأكيد هناك نوع من أنواع الميكانيكيات المحملة على زنبرك
in order to generate the amount of force that we observe,
ليولِّد هذا الكم من القوى الذي نلاحظه,
and the speed that we observe, and the output of the system.
و السرعة التي نراها, هذه الطاقة الناتجة من النظام.
So we thought, OK, this must be a spring --
و فكرنا, بالتأكيد هذا زنبرك--
the saddle could very well be a spring.
هذا السرج ممكن جدا أن يكون زنبرك أو سوستة.
And we went back to those high-speed videos again,
وعدنا مرة أخرى إلى فيديوهات السرعة الفائقة,
and we could actually visualize the saddle compressing and extending.
و يمكننا بالفعل رؤية السرج وهو ينقبض و يتمدد.
And I'll just do that one more time.
و سأعيد هذه مرة أخرى.
And then if you take a look at the video --
و إذا نظرت إلى هذا الفيديو مرة أخرى--
it's a little bit hard to see -- it's outlined in yellow.
صعب رؤيتها بعض الشئ --إنه محدد بالأصفر.
The saddle is outlined in yellow. You can actually see it
السرج محدد بالأصفر. يمكنكم رؤيته بالفعل
extending over the course of the strike, and actually hyperextending.
وهو يتمدد أثناء حدوث الحركة, ثم يزداد تمددا
So, we've had very solid evidence showing
إذن فلدينا دليل قوي للغاية يوضح
that that saddle-shaped structure actually compresses and extends,
أن هذا التكوين شبيه السرج بالفعل ينقبض و ينبسط,
and does, in fact, function as a spring.
وهو يعمل في الحقيقة كزنبرك.
The saddle-shaped structure is also known as a "hyperbolic paraboloid surface,"
هذا التركيب شبيه السرج معروف أيضا بالسطح المكافئ الزائدي,
or an "anticlastic surface."
أو سطح Anticlastic.
And this is very well known to engineers and architects,
وهذه أسطح معروفة لدى المهندسين و المعماريين,
because it's a very strong surface in compression.
لأنه سطح قوي جدا من ناحية الضغط.
It has curves in two directions,
له منحنيين في إتجاهين مختلفين,
one curve upward and opposite transverse curve down the other,
منحنى لأعلى و الأخر عكسه أحدهم على الآخر,
so any kind of perturbation spreads the forces
فأي نوع من القوى الضاغطة ستتوزع
over the surface of this type of shape.
على سطح هذا النوع من الأشكال.
So it's very well known to engineers, not as well known to biologists.
إذن فهو مألوف لدى المهندسين و لكن ليس لدى عالمي الأحياء
It's also known to quite a few people who make jewelry,
وهو أيضا معروف لدى القليلون ممن يصنعون المجوهرات,
because it requires very little material
لأنه يأخذ كمية قليلة جدا من الخامات
to build this type of surface, and it's very strong.
لبناء هذا النوع من الأسطح, كما أنه قوي جدا.
So if you're going to build a thin gold structure,
إذن إذا كنت ستصنع شكل رفيع من الذهب
it's very nice to have it in a shape that's strong.
يُفضل أن يكون في شكل قوي.
Now, it's also known to architects. One of the most famous architects
الآن هو معروف أيضا لدى المهندسين المعماريين. أحد أشهر المهندسين المعماريين
is Eduardo Catalano, who popularized this structure.
وهو إدواردو كاتالانو جعل هذا التكوين مشهورا.
And what's shown here is a saddle-shaped roof that he built
و ما ترونه هنا هو سطح مبنى بناه على شكل سرج
that's 87 and a half feet spanwise.
على إمتداد 87 قدم و نصف.
It's two and a half inches thick, and supported at two points.
و سمكه إنشين و نصف و مرتكز على نقطتان فقط.
And one of the reasons why he designed roofs this way is because it's --
و أحد الأسباب التي جعلته يصمم أسطح مباني بهذه الطريقة هو
he found it fascinating that you could build such a strong structure
أنه وجد أنه من الرائع أنه يمكنك بناء تكوين قوي كهذا
that's made of so few materials and can be supported by so few points.
مصنوع من مواد خام قليلة و مرتكز على عدد قليل من النقاط.
And all of these are the same principles that apply
وكل هذه العوامل نفسها تنطبق على
to the saddle-shaped spring in stomatopods.
الزنبرك شبيه السرج في الستومابود.
In biological systems it's important not to have a whole lot
في الأنظمة البيولوجية من المهم ألا يكون هناك الكثير
of extra material requirements for building it.
من المواد الزائدة المطلوبة لبنائها.
So, very interesting parallels between the biological
إذن فهناك الكثير من المتشابهات بين عالم الأحياء
and the engineering worlds. And interestingly, this turns out --
و عالم الهندسة. و من المثير كما يتضح--
the stomatopod saddle turns out to be the first
أن سرج الستومابود هذا هو أول
described biological hyperbolic paraboloid spring.
زنبرك حيوي علي شكل سطح مكافئ زائدي.
That's a bit long, but it is sort of interesting.
هذا إسم طويل و لكنه مثير نوعا ما.
So the next and final question was, well, how much force
السؤال التالي و الأخير كان, حسنا, ما كم القوى
does a mantis shrimp produce if they're able to break open snails?
التي يولدها قريدس فرس النبي من أجل أن يكسر الحلزون؟
And so I wired up what's called a load cell.
إذن وصلت ما يدعى بخلية تحميل (محول القوة إلى إشارة كهربية)
A load cell measures forces, and this is actually
و خلية التحميل تقيس القوى, وهذه في الواقع
a piezoelectronic load cell that has a little crystal in it.
خلية تحميل كهرو-إنضغاطية تحتوي على بعض البلورات.
And when this crystal is squeezed, the electrical properties change
و عندما تنضغط تلك البلورات تتغير صفاتها الكهربية
and it -- which -- in proportion to the forces that go in.
بشكل يعادل القوى المؤثرة عليها.
So these animals are wonderfully aggressive,
و هذه الحيوانات عدوانية بشكل هائل
and are really hungry all the time. And so all I had to do
و هم جائعون طوال الوقت. إذن كل ما تطلبه الأمر
was actually put a little shrimp paste on the front of the load cell,
هو في الواقع أن أضع بعض دهان القريدس على مقدمة الخلية,
and they'd smash away at it.
فيبدأون في ضربها.
And so this is just a regular video of the animal
و هذا فيديو عادي للحيوان وهو
just smashing the heck out of this load cell.
ينهال ضربا على خلية التحميل.
And we were able to get some force measurements out.
و بالتالي تمكنا من إستخراج قياسات للقوى.
And again, we were in for a surprise.
و مرة أخرى كانت في إنتظارنا مفاجأة.
I purchased a 100-pound load cell, thinking,
لقد إشتريت خلية تحميل تتحمل 100 باوند,معتقدة
no animal could produce more than 100 pounds at this size of an animal.
أنه لا يوجد حيوان يمكن أن يولد أكثر من 100 باوند قوى في هذا الحجم
And what do you know? They immediately overloaded the load cell.
و ماذا حدث؟ على الفور زاد على حمل خلية التحميل.
So these are actually some old data
و هذه في الواقع بعض البيانات القديمة
where I had to find the smallest animals in the lab,
حيث أحضرت أصغر حيوان في المعمل
and we were able to measure forces of well over 100 pounds
و تمكنا من قياس قوى تتخطى ال100 باوند
generated by an animal about this big.
يولدها حيوان بهذا الحجم.
And actually, just last week I got a 300-pound load cell
و في الواقع أحضرت الأسبوع الماضي فقط خلية تحميل تتحمل حتى 300 باوند
up and running, and I've clocked these animals generating
و شغلتها و قمت بالقياس لهذه الحيوانات
well over 200 pounds of force.
وهي تولد قوى تتخطى ال200 باوند.
And again, I think this will be a world record.
و مرة أخرى, أعتقد أن هذا سيكون رقما قياسيا.
I have to do a little bit more background reading,
يجب على أن أراجع أولا في هذا الموضوع
but I think this will be the largest amount of force produced
و لكنني أعتقد أن هذا سيكون أكبر مقدار من القوى يولده
by an animal of a given -- per body mass. So, really incredible forces.
أي حيوان بالمقارنة بكتلة الجسم. إذن فهي قوة هائلة فعلا.
And again, that brings us back to the importance of that spring
و هذا يعيدنا مرة أخرى لأهمية هذا الزنبرك
in storing up and releasing so much energy in this system.
في تخزين و إطلاق هذا الكم من القوة في هذا النظام.
But that was not the end of the story.
و لكن هذه ليست نهاية القصة.
Now, things -- I'm making this sound very easy, this is actually a lot of work.
أنا أجعل هذا يبدو سهلا للغاية ولكنه في الواقع عمل شاق.
And I got all these force measurements,
فقمت بتجميع كل قياسات القوى هذه,
and then I went and looked at the force output of the system.
ثم ذهبت و رأيت القوة الناتجة من الخلية.
And this is just very simple -- time is on the X-axis
وهذا سهل للغاية-- الوقت على محور السينات
and the force is on the Y-axis. And you can see two peaks.
و القوة على محور الصادات. و يمكنكم رؤية قمتين - ذروتين -
And that was what really got me puzzled.
و هذا ما حيرني للغاية.
The first peak, obviously, is the limb hitting the load cell.
القمة الأولى و كما هو واضح, هي قوة الطرف وهو يضرب خلية التحميل.
But there's a really large second peak half a millisecond later,
و لكن هناك قمة ثانية كبير جدا بعدها بحوالي نصف ميللي ثانية.
and I didn't know what that was.
و لم أكن أعرف ما هي
So now, you'd expect a second peak for other reasons,
و يمكن أن نتوقع تكوّن قمة ثانية لأي سبب
but not half a millisecond later.
و لكن ليس بد الأولى ب ½ ميللي ثانية.
Again, going back to those high-speed videos,
مرة أخرى نعود إلى الفيديوهات فائقة السرعة,
there's a pretty good hint of what might be going on.
فهناك توجد إشارة واضحة لما يحدث.
Here's that same orientation that we saw earlier.
هذا نفس التوجيه الذي رأيناه سابقا
There's that raptorial appendage -- there's the heel,
هذا هو الطرف الكاسر, ها هو الكعب,
and it's going to swing around and hit the load cell.
و سيتطوح و يضرب خلية التحميل.
And what I'd like you to do in this shot is keep your eye on this,
و ما أريدكم أن تفعلوه في هذه اللقطة هي أن تركزوا على هذا
on the surface of the load cell, as the limb comes flying through.
على سطح خلية التحميل, أثناء إنبساط و ضرب الطرف.
And I hope what you are able to see is actually a flash of light.
و أعتقد أن ما ترونه هو في الواقع ومضة من الضوء.
Audience: Wow.
الجمهور: ياه!!
Sheila Patek: And so if we just take that one frame, what you can actually see there
شيلا :و إذن لو أخذنا هذه اللقطة فقط, ما يمكنكم رؤيته بالفعل
at the end of that yellow arrow is a vapor bubble.
في نهاية هذا السهم الأصفر هو فقاعة بخار.
And what that is, is cavitation.
و هذا هو مايدعى بالتكهف.
And cavitation is an extremely potent fluid dynamic phenomenon
و التكهف هو ظاهرة مائية ديناميكية قوية جدا
which occurs when you have areas of water
و التي تحدث عندما يكون هناك مناطق من الماء
moving at extremely different speeds.
تتحرك بسرعات متفاوتة بشكل هائل.
And when this happens, it can cause areas of very low pressure,
و عندما يحدث هذا, يتسبب في مناطق من الضغط المنخفض جدا,
which results in the water literally vaporizing.
و التي تتسبب حرفيا في تبخر المياه.
And when that vapor bubble collapses, it emits sound, light and heat,
و عندما تنفجر فقاعة البخار هذه, تطلق صوت , ضوء و حرارة,
and it's a very destructive process.
وهي عملية مدمرة للغاية.
And so here it is in the stomatopod. And again, this is a situation
و ها هي تحدث مع الستومابود. و مرة أخرى هذا موقف
where engineers are very familiar with this phenomenon,
وظاهرة يألفها المهندسون,
because it destroys boat propellers.
لأنها تدمر مراوح القوارب والسفن.
People have been struggling for years to try and design
و هم يصارعون منذ سنين ليحاولوا و يصمموا
a very fast rotating boat propeller that doesn't cavitate
مراوح سفن سريعة الدوران دون أن تُحدِث تكهفا
and literally wear away the metal and put holes in it,
و أن تتسبب في تآكل المعدن حرفيا و تحفر فيه ثقوب,
just like these pictures show.
مثلما تبين تلك الصور.
So this is a potent force in fluid systems, and just to sort of take it one step further,
هذه قوى مؤثرة للغاية في الأنظمة المائية و لنأخذ هذا خطوة أخرى للأمام
I'm going to show you the mantis shrimp approaching the snail.
ساريكم الآن قريدس فرس النبي و هو يقترب من الحلزون.
This is taken at 20,000 frames per second, and I have to give
هذا تم تصويره بمعدل 20.000 لقطة في الثانية و يرجعع الفضل كاملا
full credit to the BBC cameraman, Tim Green, for setting this shot up,
في هذا لمصوِّر الBBC, تيم جرين, لتصويره هذا المنظر
because I could never have done this in a million years --
لأنني لم أكن أبدا لأتمكن من فعل هذا ولو في مليون سنة.
one of the benefits of working with professional cameramen.
أحد منافع العمل مع المصورين المحترفين.
You can see it coming in, and an incredible flash of light,
سترونه قادما, ثم ومضة هائلة من الضوء,
and all this cavitation spreading over the surface of the snail.
و كل هذا التكهف ينتشر على سطح الحلزون.
So really, just an amazing image,
إذن فهذه بحق صورة رائعة,
slowed down extremely, to extremely slow speeds.
تم تبطيئها إلى سرعات بطيئة إلى حد مذهل.
And again, we can see it in slightly different form there,
و مرة أخرى يمكنكم رؤيتها في شكل مختلف قليلا,
with the bubble forming and collapsing between those two surfaces.
و الفقاعة تتكون و تنفجر ما بين السطحين.
In fact, you might have even seen some cavitation going up the edge of the limb.
في الواقع, ربما رأيتم بعض التكهف ينتشر على حد الطرف.
So to solve this quandary of the two force peaks:
إذن لنحل معضلة زروتي المنحنى هذه:
what I think was going on is: that first impact is actually
ما أعتقد أنه يحدث هو, أن الإصطدام الأول
the limb hitting the load cell, and the second impact is actually
هو الطرف وهو يرتطم بخلية التحميل, و الإصطدام الثاني هو في الواقع
the collapse of the cavitation bubble.
إنفجار فقاعة التكهف.
And these animals may very well be making use of
و هذه الحيونات في الأغلب تستغل
not only the force and the energy stored with that specialized spring,
ليس فقط الطاقة المختزنة في هذا الزنبرك المتخصص,
but the extremes of the fluid dynamics. And they might actually be
ولكن أيضا تستغل ديناميكيات المياه المتطرفة. و هو ربما بالفعل
making use of fluid dynamics as a second force for breaking the snail.
يستخدم هذه الديناميكيات كقوى مضاعفة لكسر الحلزون.
So, really fascinating double whammy, so to speak, from these animals.
إذا فهي ضربة مزدوجة رائعة ,على حد القول بالنسبة لهذه الحيوانات.
So, one question I often get after this talk --
إذن, سؤال آخر عادة يسألونه في نهاية هذا الحديث--
so I figured I'd answer it now -- is, well, what happens to the animal?
و فكرت أن أجيبه الآن --هو ماذا يحدث لهذه الحيوانات؟
Because obviously, if it's breaking snails,
لأنه من الواضح, لو كانت تكسر الحلزونات,
the poor limb must be disintegrating. And indeed it does.
هذا الطرف المسكين لابد أنه يتفكك. وهو بالفعل يتفكك.
That's the smashing part of the heel on both these images,
هذا هو الجزء الضارب من الكعب في هاتين الصورتين,
and it gets worn away. In fact, I've seen them wear away
و هو يتآكل. في الواقع لقد رأيتهم يتآكلون
their heel all the way to the flesh.
حتى يصلوا إلى اللحم.
But one of the convenient things about being an arthropod
و لكن أحد الأشياء الملائمة في كونهم مفصليات
is that you have to molt. And every three months or so
هو أنه يجب أن يتقشر. و كل ثلاثة أشهر أو ما شابه
these animals molt, and they build a new limb and it's no problem.
تتقشر تلك الحيوانات و تكوِّن طرف جديد و بالتالي لا توجد مشكلة.
Very, very convenient solution to that particular problem.
وهو حل مثالي و ملائم للغاية لهذه المشكلة.
So, I'd like to end on sort of a wacky note.
إذن أريد أن أُنهي حديثي بملحوظة مجنونة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Maybe this is all wacky to folks like you, I don't know.
ربما كل ما قلته يبدو مجنونا لكم, لا أعرف.
So, the saddles -- that saddle-shaped spring --
هذه الأسراج, الزنبرك الشبيه بالسرج--
has actually been well known to biologists for a long time,
كان معروفا في الواقع منذ مدة لدى العديد من علماء الأحياء
not as a spring but as a visual signal.
ليس كزنبرك بل كإشارة بصرية.
And there's actually a spectacular colored dot
و هذه في الواقع نقطة ذات لون بديع
in the center of the saddles of many species of stomatopods.
في منتصف السرج موجودة في مختلف أنواع الستوماتوبود.
And this is quite interesting, to find evolutionary origins
و هذا مثير للإهتمام, أن نجد أصول متطورة
of visual signals on what's really, in all species, their spring.
للإشارات البصرية على ما هو في الواقع في كل الأنواع, زنبرك.
And I think one explanation for this could be
و أعتقد أن أحد التفسيرات لهذا ربما تعيدنا
going back to the molting phenomenon.
إلى ظاهرة التقشُّر.
So these animals go into a molting period where they're
فعندما تدخل تلك الحيوانات فترة التقشُّر حيث يفقدون قدرتهم
unable to strike -- their bodies become very soft.
على الضرب --أجسامهم تصبح هشة جدا.
And they're literally unable to strike or they will self-destruct.
وهم لا يستطيعون الضرب بالمرة و إلا سيدمرون أنفسهم.
This is for real. And what they do is, up until that time period
هذا حقيقي, و ما يفعلونه هو, قبل بداية تلك المرحلة التي
when they can't strike, they become really obnoxious and awful,
لا يستطيعون الضرب فيها, يكونوا فظيعين و بغضاء
and they strike everything in sight; it doesn't matter who or what.
يضربون كل ما يأتي أمامهم, أيا كان دون فرق.
And the second they get into that time point when they can't strike any more,
و في اللحظة التي يدخلون فيها تلك النرحلة حيث لا يستطيعون الإستمرار في الضرب,
they just signal. They wave their legs around.
هم فقط يقومون بلإشارة. يلوحون بأطرافهم.
And it's one of the classic examples in animal behavior of bluffing.
وهذه واحده من الأمثلة المعتادة في خداع الحيوانات.
It's a well-established fact of these animals
إنها حقيقة مؤكدة في تلك الحيوانات
that they actually bluff. They can't actually strike, but they pretend to.
إنهم يخادعون. هم لا يستطيعون الضرب و لكنهم بتظاهرون بذلك.
And so I'm very curious about whether those colored dots
و لذلك أنا أشعر بالفضول لمعرفة إذا كانت تلك النقاط الملونة
in the center of the saddles are conveying some kind of information
في منتصف السرج توحي بنوع من المعلومات
about their ability to strike, or their strike force,
عن قدرتهم على الضرب أو القوة التي يضربون بها,
and something about the time period in the molting cycle.
و شيء عن الفترة الزمنية في دورة التقشُّر.
So sort of an interesting strange fact to find a visual structure
إذن فهي حقيقة مثيرة و غريبة أن نجد تكوين مرئي
right in the middle of their spring.
في منتصف الزنبرك خاصتها.
So to conclude, I mostly want to acknowledge my two collaborators,
إذن لأنهي حيثي, أود أن أبدي تقديري لزملائي
Wyatt Korff and Roy Caldwell, who worked closely with me on this.
وايات كورف و روي كالدويل, الذان عملوا معي في هذا المشروع.
And also the Miller Institute for Basic Research in Science,
و أيضا معهد ميلر لأبحاث العلوم,
which gave me three years of funding to just do science all the time,
الذي أعطاني تمويل ثلاثة سنوات فقط لأبحث في العلم طوال الوقت
and for that I'm very grateful. Thank you very much.
و لذلك أنا ممتنة للغاية. شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)